Guide to the You Can Make A Difference Conference [videorecording]
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
You Can Make a Difference Conference [videorecording]
1989 Jan 22-Feb 2
V0357
Stanford University
2 Linear feet (35 videotapes)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Access Terms
Climatic changes.; Ecology--Congresses.; Environmental management.; Environmental protection--Congresses.; Videorecordings.
Collection Contents
- Opening remarks [and] keynote address, 1989 Jan 22; 1.1; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Opening remarks, Donald Kennedy, President, Stanford Univeristy. Keynote address, Peter Raven, Secretary, National Academy of Sciences.
  Peter Raven discusses a variety of environmental issues such as global warming, toxic waste dumping and exportation, population growth, tropical deforestation and biological extinction. He emphasizes the need for the US to set an example as a world leader in environmental change and international cooperation.
  Kennedy, Donald, 1931-; Raven, Peter H.; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Ecology--Congresses.; Environmental protection--Congresses.
- The Dilemma of disappearing species meeting human needs while preserving animal habitats., 1989 Jan 28; 1.2-1.3; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Panel segment followed by about 25 minutes of the "Highways or flyways" discussion. Without sound.
  The panelists discuss the Endangered Species Act, especially the politics behind the third revision of the act, issues at the federal level concerning the act, its scientific implications and its implementation and future.
  Stanford University; United States. Endangered Species Act of 1973--Congresses.; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Endangered species--Law and legislation--United States--Congresses.
- Taking it abroad who benefits from the hazardous waste trade?, 1989 Jan 28; 1.4; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Tape includes about 5 minutes of views outside Kresge Auditorium and about 11 minutes of President Kennedy's and Peter Raven's opening remarks.
  The panel discusses the controversy over the international transport of hazardous waste. They examine the cost-benefit approach and socio-political consequences of this trade, and discuss actions which the EPA and international organizations can do to regulate hazardous waste trade more consistently.
  Johnson, Jonathan.; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Hazardous waste management industry--Congresses.; Hazardous waste sites--Location--Congresses.; Hazardous wastes--Transportation--Congresses.
- Ozone depletion and acid rain international crisis or catalysts for cooperation?, 1989 Jan 28; 1.5; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  This panel discussion gives an overview of ozone depletion and acid rain, the 1988 Ozone Agreement, the use of science in decision-making, and the Canadien ozone experience. Also discussed: the ability of science to change decision-making and to question whether it is best to regulate now with undeveloped evidence or to wait for fuller evidence.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Acid rain--Congresses.; Ozone layer depletion--Congresses.
- The Politics of allocation who's getting California's water?, 1989 Jan 28; 1.6; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Label on cassette: Afternoon session: Responding at the regional level.
  Panelists discuss California's water shortage problems from their various points of view as representatives from the California Farm Bureau, the Environmental Defense Fund, Hastings College of Law and as a consultant specializing in California's water problems.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Water resources development--California.; Water rights--California.; Water-supply--California.
- The Politics of global family planning, 1989 Jan 28; 1.7; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Each of the three panelists speaks about 15 minutes on topics such as global trends in family planning, regional differences in growth, determinants of population, the significant role of women in development matters, US population policies and how they affect foreign assistance, and the impact of population growth on US policy in the specific Third World setting. The presentations are followed by about 45 minutes of discussion with the audience.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Birth control--Congresses.; Family policy--United States--Congresses.
- Logging the ancient forests of the Pacific Northwest a question of economic and ecological viability., 1989 Jan 28; 1.8-1.9; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Speakers address a number of issues including the unique and endangered animal species found only in old forest eco-systems; the perspective of the timber industry; the views of Native Americans who regard ancient forests as a source of spiritual renewal, and the various factors that go into the decision to cut or preserve old growth Douglas firs. Followed by a question and answer period with the audience.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Forest management--United States--Congresses.; Lumber trade--Northwest, Pacific--Congresses.; Old growth forests--Northwest, Pacific--Congresses.
- Debating offshore oil drilling whose economy is at stake?, 1989 Jan 28; 1.10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Tape does not include the introduction nor the opening speeches of the panelists.
  Shows the panel discussion with the audience concerning the dangers, litigation problems, and alternatives to off-shore drilling. Discussion fucuses on the conflict between regional interest and national interests.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Offshore oil industry--United States--Congresses.; Oil well drilling, Submarine--United States--Congresses.
- Highways or flyways urban development versus wetlands conservation., 1989 Jan 28; 1.11; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Panel discussion held Jan. 28, 1989 as part of the You Can Make a Difference Conference, at Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan. 22 - Feb. 2, 1989.
  Tape ends abruptly during the panel discussion.
  The panelists discuss the fate of wetlands in urban settings, especially in the San Francisco Bay Area. Specifically, they focus on the May Hughes Landing area, debating whether it is wetlands as defined under federal regulations or not. They also debate whether developing these areas would be at a significant cost to the environment.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Land use, Urban--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Land use--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Urban hydrology--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Wetland conservation--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Wetlands--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.
- A Citizen's forum on development in East Palo Alto, 1989 Jan 28; 2.1-2.2; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  Panel discussion held in East Palo Alto, California, Jan. 28, 1989 in conjuction with You Can Make A Difference Conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan. 22 - Feb. 2, 1989.
  Introduced by speaker Trevor Burrows who gives a history of environmental concerns in East Palo Alto.
  The panel discusses issues concerning the development of East Palo Alto especially in light of environmental problems. They stress community effort and group involvement in the process. Followed by a discussion period with East Palo Alto citizens.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); East Palo Alto (Calif.)--Economic conditions--Congresses.; East Palo Alto (Calif.)--Politics and government--Congresses.; Environmental protection--California--East Palo Alto (San Mateo County)--Congresses; Political participation--California--East Palo Alto (San Mateo County)--Congresses.
- Environmental policy-making in the 90's how can we make a difference?, 1989 Jan 28; 2.3-2.4; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  The panel discusses how to direct the attention of the general public to environmental issues and spur them into action to save the environment.
  Koppel, Ted, 1940-; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Ecology--Congresses.; Human ecology--Congresses.
- Living under the influence of effluents community responses to industrial air pollution., 1989 Jan 28; 2.5; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  Panel discusses the Chevron Corporation's emission of toxic waste in the city of Richmond, Calif. Focuses on the citizens' dilemma whether to compromise with Chevron to preserve the economic benefits it brings to Richmond or to eliminate the toxic waste altogether, thus decreasing their health risks but forcing Chevron out of Richmond.
  Chevron Corporation--Congresses.; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Air--Pollution--Environmental aspects--Congresses.; Industries--California--Richmond--Environmental aspects--Congresses.; Petroleum refineries--Waste disposal--California--Richmond--Congresses.; Petroleum waste--California--Richmond--Congresses.; Richmond (Calif.)--Economic policy--Congresses.
- Combating land degradation strategies for sustainable development., 1989 Jan 28; 2.6-2.7; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  Label on cassette: Morning case session: Responding to global challenges.
  Sound on tape 1 seriously degraded.
  Panelists discuss the need for domestic agricultural self-reliance and using advanced agricultural techniques to preserve sovereignty while efficiently using the land.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Agricultural ecology--United States--Congresses.; Land use--United States.; Soil conservation--United States--Congresses.; Soil degradation--United States--Congresses.
- Rainforest use in the Tropics development or destruction at what cost?, 1989 Jan 28; 2.8-2.9; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  This panel focuses on the necessity of the Amazon Rainforest for survival of the many eco-systems that support mankind, as well as its use-value for the people of South America for timber, gold and land. It also examines the right of Amazonian countries to maintain control of Rainforest areas.
  Petusek, Peter.; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Rain forest ecology--Congresses.; Rain forests--Amazon River Region--Congresses.
- Understanding and stabilizing our changing global climate, 1989 Jan 28; 2.10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  Tape does not include list of participants.
  Panel discussion concerns global warming and the greenhouse effect caused by fossil fuel combustion, deforestation, and gases such as chloroflorocarbons, methane and nitrogen-dioxide. The panel also analyses the necessity of balancing human energy needs with the need to curb global warming.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Global warming--Congresses.; Greenhouse effect, Atmospheric--Congresses.
- Environmental impacts of national security managing defense wastes in Hanford, WA., 1989 Jan 28; 2.11; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  Participants discuss the history of hazardous waste neglect at the nuclear production plant in Hanford, Wash. They examine various solutions to cleaning up chemical and radioactive residue at Hanford and identify different ways to mobelize the public to push clean-up funding through Congress.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Hanford Works (Wash.)--Congresses.; Nuclear reactors--Environmental aspects--Washington (State)--Richland--Congresses.; Nuclear reactors--Washington (State)--Richland--Congresses.; Radioactive waste sites--Environmental aspects--Washington (State)--Richland--Congresses.; Radioactive wastes--Government policy--United States--Congresses.
- Hazardous materials management, 1989 Jan 29; 1.12; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Panelists discuss the problems and issues of managing hazardous waste both at Stanford and at universities in general. They then address problems posed by hazardous materials in the industrial sector and how industries can phase out the release of chlorofluorocarbon waste in keeping with the Montreal Protocol.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Hazardous substances--California--Stanford--Management--Congresses.; Hazardous waste management industry--California--Stanford--Congresses.; Hazardous wastes--California--Stanford--Management--Congresses.
- Electronic town meetings--making a difference with televsion., 1989 Jan 29; 1.13; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Workshop held Jan. 29, 1989 as part of the You Can Make A Difference conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan.22-Feb. 2, 1989.
  With: Workshop. Speakers Dennis Rogers Martinez, Richard Ginger and David Ortiz discuss restoration of native plant communities and old growth forests in the Sinkyone five-county area above San Francisco.
  Speakers explain how television technology in electronic town meetings can be used as a means of forming consesus on environmental issues. Followed by a question-and-answer session using the electronic technology.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Communication--Technological innovations--Congresses.; Ecology--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Telecommunication policy--Congresses.; Television--Technological innovations--Congresses.
- Stanford's corporate investments, 1989 Jan 29; 1.14; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  A panel of five including John Licherman and Mike Kieschnick, address issues such as the Mid-Peninsula Open Space District volunteer projects, environmental industrial opportunities and corporate investment in this industry. Urban and open-space development are also discussed.
  Several cuts on tape.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Industries--Environmental aspects--Congresses.; Open spaces--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Regional planning--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.
- Bay Area Open Space preservation workshops., 1989 Jan 29; 1.15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Workshop held Jan. 29, 1989 as part of the You Can Make A Difference Conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan.22-Feb. 2, 1989.
  Second speaker's name illegible on tape.
  With: Running out of room: workshop.
  Speakers present a film then discuss the destruction of the San Francisco Bay Area greenbelt and possible solutions to the problem.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Fills (Earthwork)--Congresses.; Greenbelts--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Open spaces--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.; Recycling (Waste, etc.)--Congresses.; Regional planning--California--San Francisco Bay Area--Congresses.
- A Revolution in urban evolution? the sustainable city concept., 1989 Jan 29; 1.16; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Tape includes speech by Denis A. Hayes, Chairman, Earth Day 1990: "Revitalizing the Environmental Movement."
  Workshop held Jan. 29, 1989 as part of the You Can Make a Difference Conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan.22-Feb. 2, 1989.
  Explores how the programs and policies of local government can be reshaped to help solve global problems while also better accomplishing traditional health, safety, and economic development goals. Describes innovative efforts by San Jose, Calif. in energy, water, solid waste, toxics, land use, transportation, infrastructure and housing.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); City planning--Environmental aspects--California--San Jose--Congresses.; Industries--California--San Jose--Environmental aspects--Congresses.; San Jose (Calif.)--Economic policy--Congresses.; Urban policy--California--San Jose--Congresses.
- Press conference with Ted Koppel, 1989 Jan 29; 1.17; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Held Jan. 29, 1989 as part of the You Can Make A Difference conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan.22-Feb. 2, 1989.
  Tape includes about 5 minutes of a workshop, "Habitat Restoration, Part II."
  A question and answer session with environmental leaders and news correspondent Ted Koppel.
  Koppel, Ted, 1940-; Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Environmental protection--Congresses.
- Workshops, 1989 Jan 29; 1.18; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  Workshops held Jan. 29, 1989 as part of the You Can Make A Difference Conference, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., Jan.22-Feb. 2, 1989.
  Footage of some workshops is incomplete.
  Contains footage of several environmental workshops, including "Tour II. The Redwood tortoise", a bus tour of 22,000 acres of redwood forest in Big Basin State Park and a tour to the park museum.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Ecology--Congresses.; Environmental protection--Congresses.
- The Future of land development at Stanford, Part Two, 1989 Jan 29; 1.19-1.20; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  The panel discusses balancing the pressure to build and expand Stanford University with the pressure to preserve its land resources. Discussion focuses on the issue of annexation to Palo Alto versus maintaining Stanford's independance and private decision-making regarding land development.
  Stanford University; You Can Make a Difference Conference (1989: Stanford University); Land use, Urban--California--Stanford--Congresses.; Land use--Planning--Congresses.; Palo Alto (Calif.)--Congresses.
- Tour II: The Redwood Tortoise: Busing to Big Basin", 1989 Jan 29; 1.21; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
- Energy, the Environment, and the Economy, 1989 Jan 31; 1.22-1.23; 2 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
- The trash wars: Why we need to abandon the throw-away ethic, 1989 Jan 29; 2.12; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)